hello and welcome everyone it's February
2nd
2024 and we are returning for active
math stream
8.2 with Richard seron introduction to
basian mechanics free energy principle
and the paths based formalism thank you
Richard for joining for this part two
looking forward to your presentation and
discussion I have a weird Echo
um
wait are you in general synchrony with
yourself on
YouTube um wait let me
see okay perfect sorry
um okay great for hi everyone and thank
you again um Daniel so today I'm going
to present the path-based uh formulation
of the frery
principle um and I'm going to start by a
brief reminder of a couple of things we
discussed last time how however if
you're not acquainted at all with the
Notions of synchronization map of um
variational inference or L equation
it can be a good idea to uh watch the
first video and if you do so please
check the comment I posted below or I
precise um and correct few things so a
quick reminder of where we started and
where
we so basically if you consider such
sparely coupled random dynamical system
where mu corresponds to the internet
States Ita to the external States and A
and S the blocket states to respectively
the active and sensory
States and they form together the So-Cal
Mark of
blanket uh and just a bit more
vocabulary a and mu form together the
so-called autonomous States and finally
if you add the sensory states to the
autonomous States so you consider the
world Mark of blanquet plus the internal
States uh you end up with the so-called
particular States pi and the particular
States defines or constitute a particle
an agent bacteria in my schematic for
instance so if you consider such sparely
C random dynamical system you can
interpret the Dynamics of the autonomous
States in terms of perceptual and active
inference more precisely you can see
here in the bottom of my slide that the
autonomous mode minimize a free energy
function which is defined under a
generative model which is typically The
Nest density the non equilibrium steady
state density uh of your system so more
precisely the internal States mu
parameterize the density Q mu over
external States and if you look at the
path of the mode it is so that the the
free energy associated with your
variational density is always minimize
and this license is an interpretation in
terms of bean inference and about action
because you can see here that the active
uh mode is also a minimizer of the free
energy in fact it minimizes the surprise
term within free energy so that you can
see the particle as as actively sampling
unsurprising or preferred uh sensory
States sensory inputs which is active
inference and yeah if you remember well
the last video we saw that the
generative model encodes the preferences
of your system so that was basically
where we started and where we ended last
time and today I want to uh relax a c of
hypothesis so first of
all uh no steady state is assumed we
could be at steady States we could have
a well defined Nest density uh but we do
know we don't do any assumptions here
there is no steady state assumed the
second so it extends in a ways the scope
of the free energy principle the second
thing we we do is to relax the white
noise assumption this means that we
don't deal anymore with infinitely rough
fluctuations but we have uh uh fluctu
fluctuations which uh which are smooth
uh so basically we deal with colored or
correlated noise and this means that the
fluctuation the fluctuations become
differentiable up to a certain order so
basically instead of dealing just with x
and x Prime let's say you have X prime
prime and so on and so forth you have
higher dynamical orders if you will note
that this Vector X here which precisely
correspond to x x Prime and so on is
called the generalized States and the
shifted Vector this one where the first
component is X Prime we refer to it as
the generalized
motion and we also say that we work in
so-called generalized coordinates of
motion not to be confused with
generalized coordinates in analytical
mechanics so a lot of words but we just
we are just saying that the fluctuations
are smooth now and we can differentiate
uh these fluctuations up to a certain
order and this order is the order of
generalized motion and it tells you how
large the the
correlation uh length of the flu ation
is
basically I also want to introduce the
notion of generalized State space so
basically you can augment State space
with uh generalized motion so instead of
just looking at x the state of your
system you look at X Prime X prime prime
Etc and so basically we consider the
so-called generalized State
space okay
so um a lot once again a lot of words
just to say that fluctuations are smooth
now so if you look at the equation below
it seems that there there is dots and
primes here which and it it seems a bit
redundant so in fact what we call x dot
here you can view it as the actual time
derivative um that you can evaluate
anywhere for instance at t equal to and
the X Prime here is just the second
component of the momental reg
generalized states of your system uh for
instance at equal to so that if you
evaluate your time derivative at equal
to it equates indeed X Prime but this
distinction between the two will become
more clear later in the context of
generalized filtering so the cool thing
here is that if you perform a tailor
expansion of the state of your system so
you have an equation like that you can
see that generalized States constitute
the coefficient of your expansion indeed
you can see in this formula here that
you have x x Prime X prime prime Etc so
basically you do a tailor expansion
around equal to basically and the
coefficients of your expansions are
generalized States so in a way you can
see generalized states are as encoding a
path as encoding the future of your uh
of the state of your system thanks to
this taor
expansion and that's basically what I
wrote here a point in generalized State
space corresponds to a path that's
exactly what I I just said uh in virtue
of this tailor expansion here so a
consequence of that is that if you look
at the surprise of generalized State the
negative log P of vector X here and we
call it the generalized LR gen it plays
the role of an action scoring the
likelihood of a local path over the
correlation length of fluctuations so
let me break down a bit this idea once
again here
the the the order of generalized motion
depends on how smooth the noise is so
basically when you you do this taor
expansion um the um the time scale
considered here uh corresponds to the
the correlation length of your uh
fluctuations the more uh correlated your
noise is the more dynamical orders you
have in a way the larger the path
encoded by generalized
States and the corresponding surprise
the corresponding generalized lran
negative log P of vector X is a quantity
that score the likelihood of this path
in virtue of the correspondence between
points in generaliz state space and
paths so a la a last remark I want to to
do in order to be sure that uh
everything is clear here is the
following you might be a bit confused
especially if you have a physics
background uh because lents and actions
are two different things so let's take a
let's take a a step back and ask I have
a
path uh trajectory in state space if you
will and I want to compute uh a
probability density associated with a
path how should I do so the first thing
to do is to discretize
time so basically you discretize your L
equation so for the people acquainted
with stochastic calculus just notice
that it means choosing your Alpha
discretization either EO or satovi let's
say and from your your discretized L
equation you define an infin an infinite
asmal propagator just like for path
integrals in quantum mechanics an infin
alator is just a transition density
between one state to the next during a
Time window DT then you multiply the
infinite asmal propagators and then you
go to the continuous time limits and so
in a nutal that how you proceed to
compute to write down a density
associated with a path and if you do
that for instance in the simple case of
a v process where the noise is a go and
white noise you end up with the density
of a path being proportional to the
exponential of minus something and this
something we call it the action so the
smaller the action the more likely the
corresponding
path and this action in fact corresponds
to an integral over your path of
something and we call this something a
lran so a the lran is defined at any
point in time while the action
characterize the path as a wall thing so
conceptually speaking lren and actions
are two very different things but here
the key move is to uh kind of Leverage
the idea that a point in generalized
State space encode a path so that the
surprise over generalized States this
negative P of X which is defined as the
generalized LR gen plays a role indeed
of an action once again scoring the
likelihood of a local path over the
correlation length of
fluctuations so that's really the core
idea and Ling the path base formulation
of the free energy principle
so
basically uh now that we have um
introduced these ideas let's look at the
generalized lran over
autonomous States so I just want to
point out that throughout the
presentation in virtue of this
correspondence between points in
generalized States and path I will um I
will call generalized States path for
instance here I would say the lran of
autonomous path I use these words in a
interchangeable way and similarly when I
I'm dealing with with autonomous path
minimizing a generalized lran I will be
talking of uh the the path of least
action because lran play the role of an
action so be aware of this terminology
so if I'm looking at this generalized
lran of autonomous
path so negative log P of alpha the cool
thing here is that if I remove
fluctuations noise on particular state
or path so basically the particle
respond deterministically to its
environment I can rewrite this lran like
that and this formula coincides with an
expected free energy so what this
formula is all about well we can uh
reorganize it and if we do so you can
for instance write it that way so what
it means is basically
that uh the path minimizing this flan so
the most uh likely autonomous path
average over all possible sensory path
has to minimize these two terms and
these two terms are very interesting
because the first one if you look at it
is it is an expected lran over sensory
path so minimizing this lran means this
expected lran means following an
autonomous path which yields
unsurprising or preferred sensory path
and and therefore it can be viewed
indeed as an expected cost you want to
minimize and if you minimize also the
the second term this negative expected
Information Gain you can see that it is
just an expected K Divergence between
two density and these two densities the
difference between these two densities
is just that the first one here is
conditioned upon s so basically these
two densities are different if the
sensory path is informative so
maximizing this expected Information
Gain means following an autonomous path
yielding uh an informative sensory path
for instance let's say you are in a dark
room where there is an ambiguous mapping
between the hidden latent the hidden
external States and the sensory stimuli
let's say you can turn on the light and
and this action would yield informative
uh sensory inputs so that's the idea
underlying the maximization of this
expected Information Gain so this
quantity is very rich and in fact you
can do connections and links with many
established ideas for instance you can
speak of um optimal basian decisions and
optimal basian design or of uh pragmatic
value and epistemic value Etc the whole
idea here is that this
quantity entails
the preference seeking imperatives of
the particles that the first term and
the information seeking imperatives of
the par particles that's the second term
so the path minimizing this lound
kind of constitutes the best direction
of travel the optimal direction of
travel for the particle so that you can
view the particle as constantly engaging
in an optimal
Behavior okay so now having said that I
want to go back to the world idea of
synchronization map we talked about uh
last week so in fact in this setting
everything is exactly the same we just
augmented State space if you will but
you have mu parameterizing a density
everything is the same and if we
consider the internal path of list
action so the the internal path
minimizing this lran here the
corresonding parameterized density over
external path coincide with the density
of external path given sensory path so
that if you write down the corresponding
free energy
you have the first term which vanishes
in virtue of this above equality here
and free energy reduces to surprise if
you will to this lran over particular
path I'm going to so before using this
to uh derive directly the fery principle
I need
to uh briefly introduce uh the notion of
generalized filtering so in a nutshell
let's say that you have some data you
have the vector s here a sensory path
let's say and you want to compute
negative log P of s that's the quantity
you ultimately want to evaluate but it's
intractable let's say that Computing
this P ofs would require a monstrous
marginalization and you can't directly
uh compute this
guy instead you Define a proxy you
define the an upper bound this
variational free energy which is
parameterized by mu by Vector mu and you
just want to minimize this free energy
so that it coincides with what you
ultimately want to compute namely once
again negative log P of
s so in order to minimize indeed this
free energy you just follow uh a
recognition or filtering Dynamics which
is in fact a gradient sent on free
energy in fact the the exact Dynamics at
play here is this equation here so you
could ask but why don't we just have the
gradient term here nabla F why do do we
have a s term here this D mu by the way
about this D mu here what is it well the
Matrix D here is just this Matrix with
ones here in in this uh line so basic
basically if you have a vector X let's
say x x Prime X prime prime and so on
and you want um to to to get from this
Vector a shifted Vector X Prime the
motion if you will you just have to
apply this Matrix D here and on X and it
gives you indeed X Prime and so
basically you can view this D mu here as
being equal to Mu Prime
basically and the idea is that you when
once you the gradient term here is
minimized when free energy is minimized
so we we look at the stationary solution
of this equation if you will m dot
coincide with d mu and let me just
explain why we don't just have the
gradient term here if we only had the
gradient term without the DM here we
would go down on free energy until a
minimum is reached and basically we
would have the first component of the
vector mu being non zero but all the
higher dynamical orders would be zero
because we are at the minimum of free
energy and we don't move anymore but
here it is a wall Vector mu which
parameterize free energy and we don't
want all the entries to be zero and we
want an equation which guarantees that
so that we add an additional term in the
equation so that's basically in a
natural what generalized filtering is
all
about and by the way note that if you
consider the path of lift action of uh
some process X you can write it in a
very similar fashion the only difference
is that here the quantity minimize is
just the the this L generalized lran
here whereas it was free energy in the
context of generalized
filtering and by the way we just saw
before that if uh we that if we consider
the path the internal path of fist
action the corresponding free energy
here associated with the density the
internal path of f action parametri it
reduces to the
lran so
that when we write down the equations
here uh verified by the autonomous path
of least action you can directly
identify free energy to the lran and we
basically have the same equations that
in generalized filtering so
basically um if we look at the
autonomous path of list action you can
uh interpret the Dynamics of of the
internal path of list action so in terms
of basian inference which takes the form
here of a basian filtering
scheme and note that if we remove
fluctuations on particular States or
paths that the definition of dealing
with a conservative
particle the autonomous path will
coincide with the autonomous path of
least
action and note that ignoring
fluctuations might be relevant when it
comes to very large particles
uh where you can um so to very large
particle you can cause grain and you can
uh check these papers here where where
they try to average out fluctuations
using a renormalization group
approach so in the end we find the free
energy principle just as before uh but
the difference is that here the the the
the beian inference takes the form of a
beian filtering scheme but otherwise we
still end up with a variational
principle accounting for the
the for the perceptual and active
inference that the particle do so okay
now I want to do a bit of zology of
typology let's say I said last time that
this pass coping architecture here was a
canonical Spar coping architecture but
it was not a definitive feature of the
free energy principle and that we could
look at other Spar coupling architecture
and I want now to look at various Spar
coupling architecture so the most simple
ones you could imagine is one like that
where you don't have active States so
basically um the the you only have the
mark of blocket is only made of sensory
state in the end you can still uh uh
write down the internal path of list
action like that but it will the idea
that the particle en Cod believes about
its external environment it will not
manifest to an observer because by
definition an observer has only access
to the mark of
blanket and that's what this quote is
all about when it says that whether
internal Paths of Leist action
parameterized beliefs about external
paths and therefore minimize varal free
energy can only manifest via active
states that is in active particles and
of course no one would attribute any
form of agency or sentence to a simple
piece of rock for
instance so if we move to the realm of
active particles now we basically have
the equations we uh studied before but
the difference here with this pass
coupling architecture is that the active
states do not directly interact with the
external States and the sensory states
do not directly interact with the
internal States this uh sparse coupling
architecture is quite interesting
because it reminds I would say it
reminds the the way a bacteria is
coupled with its environment because you
would have like the outter M brain with
all the transmembrane proteins The
receptors whatever which would
correspond to the sensory States and
then you would have the underlying
cortex filaments which mediate Med many
aspects of biotic actions so I like I
like very much this uh architecture here
but we can even go further in the
sophistication and consider the
so-called strange particles the only
move here is that
we don't have any Arrow from s to Ita
but more importantly we don't have any
Arrow from a to Mu so the active states
do not directly uh influence the
internal
States and this is interesting because
it means that now the internal States
alone are independent of both the active
and the external States when conditioned
upon the sensory state so so from the
point of view of the internal States the
active States become a latent cause just
like the external states of the sensory
of the sensory
States so basically everything is the
same you can write down a variational
density parameterized by the internal
States or path but now it is over both
the external and the active path and so
we have this free energy here we call it
the generalized free energy uh G but
everything is the same it's just the
variational free energy associated with
our recognition density which is over
both external and active path so that in
the end we have this equation here where
you have in the equation of the internal
path of list action the gradient on um
on G here so it's very interesting
because it basically means that the
internal
path infers infers and in fact
cause uh the its own action um the the
its own action which then cause its
sensory uh inputs so and I'm quoting
here the paper which introduced the
notion of strange particles you can view
the active particle the active path
sorry as realizing the sensory
consequences of the inferred action so
basically such a particle kind of author
its own action its own uh action and so
the idea here is that the particle kind
of infer its its own course of
action which will yield preferred
sensory outcomes so it's really a form
of planning of inference
strange
particles do planning as inference so
that's that's uh quite cool and in fact
we can even go go a bit further
and assume a certain level of sparcity
within internal States so you would have
this mu1 here which influence mu2 but
not the other way around so from the
point of view of the worldall uh
internal States everything is the same
you have it parameterized all together
density Q mu and by the way under a
meanfield approximation you can write it
that way where you would have q mu1 and
Q mu2 here but the very cool thing here
is that from the point of view of mu1
alone well mu1 is independent of mu2 a
and ITA when condition upon s and you
can view mu1 alone as parameterizing a
density over me2 a and EA and we call it
that way with the over script M so
basically Q mu1 is a density or a belief
about mu2 and therefore about Q mu2 so
that you can view this q mu1 m as a
metacognitive belief because it
constitute a belief about a belief
because it's a belief about Q mu2 so
that just by assuming this simple
architecture within internal States we
end up with a um minimal beian mechanics
let's say of metacognition and it also
uh introduces the notion of
metacognitive particles so I think
that uh what ban mechanics is all about
meaning uh translating cognitive
abilities in simple physical term it Con
constitutes in a way a physics of
cognition if you will so H having said
that uh thank you very much and
especially thanks to all these guys here
which who uh helped me a lot uh
understanding uh the free energy
principle and especially the path based
formulation of the free energy principle
thank
you all right
awesome
great a lot of ways I could start but
it's so interesting that
um how smoothly the path-based
continues on so maybe could you give a
remark on just the timeline in the
literature which one of these State and
path base were developed just roughly
like in which ordering was one first or
how did happen
yeah yeah so I'm not an expert on the
history of the free energy principle but
I know that thinking in terms of uh path
and in terms of generalized filtering
has been around for um forever in fact
in the literature but about um the most
um I would
say uh definitive formulation in such
terms I would say that the most
important paper is um well I have it
here uh it's called path
integrals well where it is uh I can see
it
um well uh firston physics of Life
review
2023b
particular yeah exactly this paper here
path integrals particular kinds and
strange things which is also the paper
so we which introduced
um all this typology of particles and it
kind of really uh formulated the frery
principle that way um so I think that's
pretty much a very very important paper
and actually the one which introduce the
notion of metacognitive particles the
one of uh length and
Lars um this one towards the bean
mechanics of metacognitive particles the
last one it is actually a commentary a
short commentary very easily readable of
the path integral paper we just
mentioned um and also I would say that
in the 2022 paper the fre energy
principle made seem simpler but not too
simple uh published in 2023
actually uh it is mainly it mainly
focused on the state based formulation
but it it also talk about um paths and
generalized
States um so it it it's also a very nice
um very nice papers and it kind of deriv
the whole thing from scratch so I think
this paper is also very very
important um and yeah I think basically
in the last two or three years there
have been many
papers uh reformulated ating the free
energy principle or grounding it in in
in in solid mat and so on so it's I
think currently and let's say the the
few years which followed from the 2019
monography of car friston it has been
very important years about when it comes
specifically to beijan mechanics and the
actual physics underlying the fre energy
principle thank you yeah I'll just
restate that I think there's a few great
points to explore so even as early as
the early
2000s there was the notion that there
was like physics of Consciousness
physics of cognitive systems a free
energy principle for the brain there
were physics-based
equations in the 2010 friston paper
there's a big tree with all these
different inference
algorithms however they were all just
kind of branches on that tree little bit
more evocatively or or aspirationally
but not not formally then dot dot dot
2019 free energy principle for
particular physics and the reading group
and all the work around that and then
especially in the last year since then
um I think that
the the decision and the move that you
made to lead with the state
based and then almost nothing had to be
said today of course it was a great
presentation but you said it all that we
potify the path we make paths into
points in a given
space um and so I was thinking about
like being in a car and then there's one
path where like my first derivative is
one for two seconds and then it stops
and then that was that path and there's
another path where my first derivative
is one for 4 seconds and then I stopped
and so all of those different paths
which do take take the car to different
locations they are also just points in
this generalized
space and then there's this
interpretation of those coefficients as
the Taylor series
expansion but it just shows how
versatile the formalism is because it
can
take points in arbitrary State spaces
which means yes you can imagine
arbitrary State spaces that correspond
to Taylor series expansions or
potentially other kinds of
constructs what do we get from
paths so in fact I think there are um a
couple of things which uh motivated such
a formulation because when I mean about
the
usual uh State based formulation we
talked about last
time there was um many critics many I
mean it was there was many debates for
instance about the question about the
nest density being at steady state is it
really relevant when it comes to real
system to real biological systems for
instance so there was many uh things
which are now um addressed by the path
based formulate
formulation uh because as we saw we
relaxed a couple of hypothesis and also
the second thing which is very very much
at the core of the path based
formulation as you said is I mean the
the the fact to move from um states to
path to path which are in fact encoded
by generalized States it allows you
to to to speak of the future uh to the
to speaks to the Future Path so that you
can develop a physics of particles
planning for instance which was not at
all the case with the previous
formulation so having such extension of
the scope of the free energy principle
it allows you to to literally describe
the basian mechanics of particles
planning um and and so it's the fact to
think in terms of path as opposed to
States it allows you to develop a
physics of let's say higher other
cognitive abilities I would say uh so
it's it's definitely very very cool and
uh a great achievements let's
say responding to that um I would say
planning is possible in the state-based
formalism it's just more of a Brute
Force tree branching
engineering problem so it's almost like
in the state base formalism there was a
physics of the perception action
Loop and then there were classical
computer science ways to deal with the
branching of planning just like a chess
algorithm like how many depth deep in
the time Horizon and then there's all
these secondary strategies for branching
uh and pruning that surch tree but
there's kind of like few to none in
terms of the guarantee of the um time
Horizons of policy you just kind of had
to enumerate all the possible
options um but the realtime
colonel was physically grounded and
beautiful and then planning had to be a
little
bit
enumerated but when we have the path as
a atomic entity
um then we can kind of extend
the the Elegance or the Simplicity that
we were dealing with states in the
moment but now our state in the moment
is like a tailor expansion and this
comes up a lot in the distinction
between the discrete time and the
continuous time models like figure 4.3
in the textbook where in a discreet time
model if you want to plan 100 time steps
in the future there's some variable you
know T sub 100 like you literally are
making a prediction and but you have no
prediction for T sub
99.5 you're just making discrete
predictions whereas a Taylor series even
a tailor series for a super complex
function and you're only going to go two
levels of differentiation in you will
have a prediction even for any point it
might be radically wrong but you get the
whole support from negative to positive
Infinity basically for
free without guarantees of it being
accurate but it's like you've kind of
pinned yourself to the
timeline and then every single
derivative that you take is giving you a
better handle on that path for sure
you'll never do
worse and so that is like
so similar yet also very different
setting it's true that I said that the
time scale scale considered was
basically the correlation length of
fluctuations on the number of the order
of generalized motion but in principle
your tailor expansion apply to I mean
it's
infinite but of course above beyond the
correlation length of fluctuations it
becomes wrong and I also want to say
about what you said said in the
beginning uh about the state based the
the state based formulation yeah it's
it's true and actually in um in the
paper the free energy principle simpler
but not too simple they um they uh so
you can write down the the action of a
path so here we we have a Goan white no
everything is is um so we are really in
the state based formulation of the FP
you can write the action of a path and
you realize that it coincides with an
expected free energy as well so you
don't need to be in the path base
formulation to uh go to to get to the
expected free energy thing um which
equates the action of autonomous path or
here in our path base formulation it
equates a generalized lran of uh
autonomous path so so yeah could you
come back to where there was the
generalized
lran so this is
a
um okay maybe uh one before
this yes okay thank
you for those of us outside of the
nonactive physics world how is action
used what does Action correspond to in
physical systems when we're talking
about action as generalized
lran is this the same thing as what
we're talking about with policy
selection and movement and embodied
action how is this physics concept of
action being
used so first of all I would say that
there is I mean it depends on what we're
talking about um when it comes to
actions in lren we we usually think of
um anal analytical mechanics but here it
would be more in the context of
stochastic calculus and in the context
of stochastic calculus and path
integrals in stochastic
calculus the action is just a quantity
which scores the likelihood of a path so
if for instance the density of a path is
uh the exponential of minus something
you would call by identification this uh
thing the action and basically the
smaller the action the more likely the
path because the higher the density of
your path and vice versa so by the way
when we we're saying for instance here
that the action is equal to I mean we
Define it as negative log density of a
path in principle if the density I mean
when it comes to the usual definition of
the of the action if I write my density
as a normalization factor times the
exponential of minus the
action then if I take the negative log
of this density I would have the regular
action plus something and usually this
uh constant is dis is
disgarded we um we just don't consider
it so that the action reduces to
negative log density of a path but
conceptually speaking this action is
very different from the idea of lran
because basically the ACT I mean usually
speaking the action is the integral over
time over your path of um of a quantity
called the lran so at every point in
time there is a quantity defined and
this is the lran which is defined at any
point in time while the action is a
quantity which characterize path as W
thing so conceptually speaking actions
and lents are very different things lran
once again are defined at any point in
time while the
action okay LR was defined at any point
in time while the
action okay all wait a few seconds for
Richard to rejoin if you're watching
live please feel free to write questions
in the
chat and we'll look at
them did you're back it's all good yeah
lran is defined at every point in time
and then the
action and basically
um so in order to just uh
answer what you well uh here yeah when
you said that is it different from the
notion of action when in the active
iterature for instance and so on here we
we use the word action
uh but it has nothing to do with the
notion of action like acting in the
world Etc so yeah for the people who
never um meet this concept so it can be
super confusing I guess when you uh when
you when you read page and mechanics
papers you you don't really know what
action is a we're talking about but yeah
they are very different I know it's
funny like
each path has an action value the
negative log
density that in a way summarizes what we
could say are the actions that that path
entails but yet the actions or the
affordances that are taken on that path
that are summarized by the physics
action um so there's
yeah um also yeah very um Cutting Edge
with reviewing the typ ology of
particles and the dasta and saned Smith
metacognitive particle um that shows I
think a few things one that often there
are implicit Concepts and qualitative
Concepts that are built up like long
have people said that there is a
continuity of modeling between rocks and
societies for example popes and
plaintiffs and Plankton and all these
other funny things that that friston at
all say but not until this
paper did we see the simple the
conservative and the
strange and
then with that Target article just with
the dasta and sanvit Smith work they
kind of take that in another level and
like
compose off to the side and now we can
go into a metacognitive depth
combining back to like the hierarchical
nested meta awareness work of saned
Smith from
2021 so it's just very cool how there's
like a kind of earlier first
pass
qualitative
intuition and then the Empirical
research question is like where can we
build the High-Speed Rail
lines and this is like the blue print
for the highspeed rail now and then the
next level will be like actually making
the simulations or whatever it is to
kind of show that this is not just
something that you can make in
PowerPoint but this is actually
something where the rabbit is going to
be evincing some kind of behavior that
it couldn't otherwise but it's kind of
like that's like in a way it's not the
only way but it is like an agenda
between the um intuitive to the
sketched and just builds
forward in these ways that are being
reviewed pretty clearly and changing on
a month by
month yeah and I think I mean this I I
mean this agenda of
translating um Concepts like cognitive
abilities and stuff in simple physical
terms is quite interesting and I I mean
we we discussed it on by message on
Discord but
it's it's um it would be cool and it's
it's coming it's happening but uh it's
it could be cool to for the this uh ban
mechanics this field to be more known
and recognized by the physics Community
because if you meet like a regular
physicist working for instance in the
physics of complex systems on or in
biological physics or bioh physics and
stuff like that it I mean you like a
0.999 probability that he never heard of
basan mechanics while we have a world
agenda to to to to to following is I
think there is way more to to be done
it's like the the down of this uh field
of this agenda let's say so I think the
the next years are quite exciting in
that
regard I I totally agree like one meme
or theme on that for me is like the base
graph on the screen on the table it is
what it is and then there's the second
level where we annotate or assert that
graph with cognitive phenoma like well
this
graph reflects attention or awareness of
attention or metacognition or regret or
whatever we're modeling we kind of make
an assertion about the base graph
and like you said it's the dawn this
isn't the answer on metacognition this
is like one very
Snappy
very um following in line way of
modeling
metacognition there's no end there's no
end to that question of how do you model
metacognition and so then it's just like
every time in a psychology paper or any
we see like a cognitive phenomena which
which can include everything from
anticipation you know past present
future that's like our Keyhole to bridge
with this generalized unifying
perspective on cognitive
systems yeah I totally agree this work
is really um this work here on the slide
is very like a first work but I mean
when it comes to metacognition for
instance I mean I'm not an expert at all
but there are many Concepts I don't know
m actions cognitive effort whatever
there are many things many layers and
the the I think like translating all of
these concepts of these phenomena
processes whatever into an actual basing
mechanics is um is really like the
what's coming in fact I think in the
next years so and yeah we'll see and and
as you said beyond the analytical work
there is also the simulations work
examples whatever um so yeah I think
there are many many Works to to be done
and which are coming in the in the next
years I totally
agree yeah kind of analogy that brings
to mind is like early in the periodic
table not saying that we're studying
material phenomena um or even like
elements are material phenomena but it's
kind of like well the has Vision taste
and hearing so if we've
identified uh memory in vision and taste
there's like a missing element for maybe
it's not there maybe the memory for
hearing is zero or maybe it's something
very complex but it's like but there's a
space there it's like there should be um
a rare earth metal in the fourth row
there should be an attention variable on
this and so it's kind of like a higher
dimensional periodic
table where because we know about
certain patterns that are either kind of
convergently arising in the real world
because of what is life
or they're um convergently arising
because we choose to model things a
certain
way then that brings a huge amount of
concordance and juxtoposition
like to the field of chemistry whereas
previously there might have been air
chemistry and water chemistry and fire
chemistry and then there'd be like oh
but what happens when you throw water on
a fire or what happens when the air in
the room Burns Out there'd be like these
edge cases where it's like oh we don't
do
that but that's what's happening when we
don't have the unified model for
cognitive systems people will kind of
study one phenomena or character of a
system to its limits but the limits of
any phenomena in our highly
woven life
forms like you don't chase it to the end
if you're studying foraging in the ant
colony it's not like there's a okay that
was the end of the rainbow foraging is
over it's like oh well foraging is
related to nursing and then that's
related to this and the weather it it
never just
simply terminates with the
inquiry and um um possibly that could
reflect the extremely early stage of
this
formalization possibly there are
fundamental unknowns and
adjacencies in
our epistemic
situation yeah and I think I mean few
years ago the idea of kind of extending
physics
to in order to have an actual physics of
cognition it would be like uh crazy like
the holy grail and the fact that we have
this early works is quite an achievement
and I would also say that what's
interesting here is that we already do
have um
formal uh models of many um of many
cognitive um phenomena for instance you
were talking about the the paper of last
about metacognition um so we have
very precise and formal active inference
models for instance of many different
phenomena like metacognition and so on
so in a way we kind of already know what
we should end up with and the idea is uh
how to do how to play for instance with
the sparcity within internal States in
order to go to get back or to rederive
or
refind what people are already modeled
in a different literature earlier so
that's kind of the Dynamics I think um
so yeah we'll see in the next year how
it goes yeah that's a great point a few
more thoughts on that like a lot of the
uh adjacencies and
generalizations mathematicians and
physicists and statisticians they're
experts in this like if it was a fixed
number see if it could be variable if
there wasn't a variance see if you can
add a variance if it was this kind of
distribution swap it out for like there
are these kind of syntactic moves that
barely
require much more than just like yeah
these are the swaps we make like this is
what it looks like to generalize a
theory it's like we could add a variance
on you know all all so those kinds of um
familiar moves and then
um so much can be explore on this topic
but when we think about a physics of
cognitive systems or a physics of
cognition sometimes I feel like I have
one foot like is it's like tied or
somehow trailing with the reductionism
like it's hard to escape the material
basis and it's also not clear if we want
to escape the material basis because of
physics of cognitive systems on one hand
it might address this kind of like
Thermo
info neant Tropic schinger what is life
question about persistence and Order of
kind of Quasi
crystals or leave all that mess separate
mess and
Beauty the pure basian mechanics if we
just say okay now we're in the map we're
we're leaving the territory behind we're
not going to talk about the actual
calories and the thermodynamics we're
just on the map and imag massive prior
with a little attention is like a piece
of sand hitting a mountain and a very
loose prior with a highly attended to
data point is like a bowling ball you
know smashing through a small little um
heap of sand so it's like there's a
physics to the
Collision of incoming data and prior
which is the basian
setting so it's interesting that there's
a sort of
map basian
mechanics that kind of noncontroversial
describes the Collision
of priors of different mass in a way and
then the tantalizing question or
connection is whether that is like one
in the same or an enabling factor or a
downstream factor of this actual
Thermo
informational autop poesis for living
systems if if I may add something I
think here the uh I mean an interesting
point is that if you have for instance
um I mean I I don't want to to go there
really but if I we have if I have a
software which is which can be
implemented by many sort of Hardwares
for inance
um and this idea was actually a lot
debated in the when it came to
functionalism and stuff like that but
anyway here the such basian mechanics in
a way it's the physics of
um how
um
um how the the overall system should
behave but we so there is for instance
the minimization of this uh free energy
functional but we are not saying how the
here we we do not
um uh explicitly
say how the system uh actually does the
computations we just say that a sply
coer romal system has somehow to do that
stuff and in a way it is neutral about
what
um what the the actual system is made of
um it's like when we say that the fery
principle is more a framework than a
process Theory or stuff like that um but
I mean I I I
um I don't know very much about these uh
questions I I I think that's that's a
great point it's like that's why a
program or an operating system can be
run when a different processor is
brought in just within a kind of
classical Computing setting um as a
cognitive mapping or cognitive modeling
framework like we don't know if that
rabbit is a real biological rabbit that
rabbit might be a deep fake rabbit and
we're interacting with it through a
video channel and we think that we're
doing behavioral research on a real
rabbit but it's just a really convincing
synthetic data rabbit um we don't no
because we're only getting the
observations that we're getting and then
we can tell any number of possibly
compatible stories or interpretations
about the data we're getting and to say
more or to go further like that's
stepping past the boundary of the actual
observations we're making which is great
like we want to propose hypotheses for
what we're not directly observing that's
the whole point of latent States and
everything and yet there is this line
where it's like you can kind of falsely
push the known knowns Beyond where they
really
are um and it seems like one example of
that is going down and
specifying the actual mechanistic basis
of a
given computational
function and that that's if that's to
specify then the work itself is to
specify it however at the framework
level the
framework's
absence of that kind of a material
substrate like that's the feature that's
not a A lacina in the
framework that is
like there's the USB stick and then
there's where you can plug it in that is
the plugin to any system and if there
was something something already pre-
plugged in there like well it has to
happen on Turing computer or it can't
happen on Turing
computer that would have just hobbled
the scope of
applicability by welding together what
doesn't need to be welded and I mean if
anything this is a um journey and a a
challenge about proper
articulation and about how sparity
and
nuancing which are connected to
what brings us cognitive phenomena so
it's
like many things to learn and reflect
on yeah and if I may add a a related
remark um about
the the question of having a topown
approach as as opposed to bottom of
approach I think sociologically speaking
and historically speaking it's very
interesting that the people who started
developing basan mechanics are people
who are not like supposed to be
professional
physicist because I think when you it
comes to like super
emergent kind of phenomena like
cognition whatever
um the the people who was training is
precisely to learn uh about cognition
about agencies the people who kind of
know everything about what it takes to
be an agent and so on these guys are
neuroscientist basically so they because
they know what agency entails they can
be the good ones to propose an actual
ban mechanics which is a very uh top
down approach whereas if you go to the
labs in like a physics of complex
systems lab and stuff like that people
are pretty much um bottom up they will
for instance oh I I want to study the
brain so I'm going to write down the
upfield model for instance so a kind of
izing model where up is an activated
neurons and down um uh uh uh non not
activated neurons and so I will have
this very this very much bottom up
approach and I can which is super
interesting and super important but when
it comes to this very much uh emergent
Behavior Uh the the very emergent
phenomena of the brain metacognition
blah blah blah I can study for like five
centuries the upfield model I will never
get any insight about the emerging
behavior of the brain
and um and um so I think
here you have to have
a a top down approach you have to write
a very generic uh L equation and because
you're a
neuroscientist and because you know what
it takes to do an inference to to be an
inference machine you're like ah
conditional independencies is very
different is very important sorry so
let's try to inject in my L equation
some level of spse coupling and then
boom you have the free energy principle
so even So sociologically speaking
What's Happening Here might be super
weird like these guys are not supposed
originally at least to be physicist and
they are supposed to like kind of
generate the next chapter of physics how
weird is that but in fact in fact I
think they were precisely the the good
people to do that um so yeah it's it's
quite interesting I think there might be
oh that's a great point there might be a
fun history with physician physician
heal thyself and the alliance of
medicine and physic that's one point
another point is um low road and high
road and sometimes the the disciplinary
or the ingroup conversation is like very
low road and then the idealistic and
aspirational is like High Road
it doesn't exactly map to those but I'm
thinking of like somebody says like I
want to drive somewhere I want to travel
somewhere there is no material basis for
that travel yet they're not there
there's no path there's no car and then
in the mechanic shop it's like well we
have this tool this object like the low
road we're so surrounded by the low road
that it supports this incremental
research agenda using the tools and
approaches that we have and their
materiality whereas someone from outside
the
field um like comes to the ant
researcher it's like have you had the
ants build this new thing and it's like
well we we weren't even on that path but
now that's like a new North Star and
that can now
draw work in that direction and so it's
kind of like the the low road building
out and then like the kind of um the
draw of the adjacent possible in the
imagination that the high road kind of
grounds in all right I'll ask a question
from the live chat Susan
asks what can one equation contain I'm
imagining how to interpret and translate
self-modeling how to approach foraging
resources and
opportunities uh can you can you repeat
please yes it's an open-ended question
so yeah feel free to however you like
what can one equation contain I'm
imagining how to interpret and translate
self-modeling how to approach foraging
resources and
opportunities so I I I I could not
answer the second part of the question
but if I can pick up on uh
about the question of
uh what what these equations are all
about which is a bit what you asked last
week like what Works do does the
framework do what these equations
contain or
whatever um if you actually simulate a
sparely coule random dynamical system
and actually there are there already are
examples out there for instance in the
paper called
um
uh uh Mar stochastic chaos and Mark of
blankets if I remember well with Thomas
for and car fron and others they
simulate a a coupled uh low rent
um
um uh systems if I if I remember well
and if you do um simulate such systems
which verifies sear SP coping
architecture You observe the Behavior
which is described by your equations and
if for instance you remove fluctuations
on particular
States so uh well your simulation which
follows the path of list action which is
given by your equation so it's it's um
it's it's uh it does really work in the
sense that it does describe indeed
something it's really a physics in fact
of such uh SP
systems great question I think we could
Explore More on what an equation can
contain but I'm just kind of struck by
that there's like a latent
large set of
um to be clarified axioms and
conclusions and so on and when we see
like one equation written
here it's kind of like we're just seeing
like one glimpse
or one facet it's not like the other
equations aren't in effect but sometimes
it's a little unclear which equations
are
relevant but in an
equation
um we see a symbolic
expression that within a given Quantum
reference frame other otherwise the Q
and the a wouldn't mean anything like
with within a semantic reference frame
the equation is just kind of like a
check it's like if
it's like it it's there's probably many
ways that we can kind of explore what it
does but it's true that I mean I think
many peoples
who in addition don't necessarily have
uh mathematical background or whatever
they have been I I I mean I'm not an
expert in the history of the fery
principes but a lot of people have been
confused especially in the early steps
where it was as l
say it many times where it when it was
even more an intuition than a solid
framework properly grounding it solid
mat so
people did get a bit confused I think by
with the mat but now it's we have more
and more worked examples
simulations um solid mat Etc so it's
it's quite um quite
nice okay in closing we have explain it
like I'm a 10-year-old now that that
response may reveal more about what
somebody thinks 10-year-olds are like
but now that we've been on this two-part
Journey you know dotzip it and close it
Richard so explaining you mean uh about
what I just said like uh
before just both sections or just our
whole projects now that now that we can
look back and all the incredible quality
summaries that we've
provided how do we just cap it and move
forward with the child
yeah so I think everything we did here
so both in this presentation and the
previous one is
um so basically we can so if I I I would
so in order to take in the most um
intuitive and simple ways I would say
that very simply put a system is just
um it's just
um it's just some things interacting
let's say so it would literally
correspond to a system as we use this
word in a in a daily basis uh
uh pen is a system an organism or any
piece of
uh any collection of things interacting
with each other we I'm I can say this is
the system I just have to precisely
delimitate um and and say what are the
boundary of my system and given a system
which has a certain Dynamics um certain
laws physical laws telling you how your
system behave how the things move around
and so
on and now so my system can be alone
like an asteroid in space let's say or
it can be connected to each to other
things I recognize as other
systems um two things can Collide two
different things systems can collide
with each other etc for instance and now
if I assume several systems which are
connected meaning that they
Cally interact with each other in a
certain SP
way so basically in my schematic you
would have for instance a system on the
right a system on the left and a sub
system in the middle so you have many
subsystems coal interacting in a sparely
way for instance mu doesn't interact
with ITA if I take a bacteria for
instance it does move around and
interact with other things outside the
bacteria but at the same time within the
bacteria under the outer membrane there
there is also stuff which do not
interact because that interact with the
outside let's say and so if you have
such uh sparse coupling architecture as
we
say we and were and in in in a more
technical term terms we would say that
the inside
is uh independent of the outside when
conditioned on the intermediate system
let's say so if we have such sply
coupled system dynamical
system uh we see mathematically speaking
we derive the fact that your system has
to behave in a certain way and in fact
when you do have such spy coule
dynamical system you realize that
everything uh appears to
uh I mean if you look at for instance
internal States mu here the Dynamics of
this
system uh can be interpreted in terms of
beian inference meaning that this system
can be viewed as encoding a density over
its external States for instance and if
I had to Define in a very simple way
what it means to parameterize or to
encode a
distribution I would say that
um your
um
um the
various uh parameters which Define your
system for instance uh I said earlier
that a system could be anything a pen an
asteroid whatever there are variables
which specify its St for instance
temperature pressure shape whatever I
have a set of variables and I can view
these variables these numbers literally
as I can take them and manipulate them
as parameters of a mathematical quantity
I I I can deal with and yeah so I'm not
sure if I failed in trying
to put it in in a very very simply terms
but I I hope it makes
sense it was a awesome Richard thank you
for
um working to bring us these twin
gems in the distillation work and really
helping like consolidate and
sediment on one hand a long history of
dynamical systems and physics and on the
other hand papers coming out two weeks
ago as well so hopefully we'll continue
the adventure
and um see you
around yeah thank you and thank you for
the chat questions on the chat cool
peace everyone
bye bye thank
you
I